またそんな顔して 唇噛み締めて
mata sonna kao wo shite
There you go, making that face again,
biting onto your lips.
kuchibiru kamishimete
弱さを隠してるけど
yowasa wo kakushiteru kedo
You're hiding your weak side,
その瞳の奥 うずくまる君が
sono hitomi no oku
but deep in those eyes,
uzukumaru kimi ga
I can see you cowering.
本当の心なら
honto no kokoro nara
If you had a true heart,
思って 泣いて 一人で 不安で
omotte, naite, hito yonde, fuwande
you would care, cry, call for someone and worry.
なんで 痛いの 持ってんだ
nande itai no mottenda
Why are you holding onto the pain?
僕に そっと 預けてよ
boku ni sotto azukete yo
Share some of it with me.
直ぐじゃ無理と思うのならば
sugu ja muri to omou no naraba
If you don't think it's possible right away,
少しずつでいい
sukoshi zutsu de ii
you can do it slowly, bit by bit.
翼の無い僕等はきっと
tsubasa no nai bokura kitto
We don't have wings,
tobenai toki mitsuketeru dake
but I'm sure we're only finding times that we can't fly.
飛べないと 決め付けてるだけ
koe no kagiri kimi wo yobu yo
I'll call for you to the limits of my voice
声の限り君を呼ぶよ 迷わないように
mayowanai you ni
so that you won't get lost.
フワリ心舞い上がれ あの風に乗せて
fuwari kokoro maiagare
Soar up to the sky with your gentle heart,
ano kaze ni nosete issei erose
ride on that wind, and get it all at once.
Natsume
Yuujinchou
あーりゃりゃ 完全に干上がってるわ
It completely dried up.
It was a pretty dry season this year.
今年は空梅雨だったからな
これじゃ釣りは無理か
I guess we can't go fishing, then.
That's amazing.
すごいな 見ろ 夏目
Look, Natsume.
Ah, it's the village that was submerged because of the dam.
ああ ダムに沈んでた村が
双葉村だよ
It's the village of Futaba.
あ 人がいる
There's someone there.
Look, by that house's window.
ほら あの家の窓の所
よせよ 夏目
Come on, Natsume, there can't possibly be anyone there.
あんな所に人がいる訳ないだろう
ああ それもそうだな
I-I guess you're right.
They can't see it?
見えないのか
じゃあれは…
Then it's a...
Natsume!
夏目
どうした 夏目
What's wrong, Natsume?
Hey, Natsume!
夏目
おい 大丈夫かよ
Are you all right?
The Swallow at the Water Bottom
夢
A dream?
So you got dizzy?
目を回したって 夏目
軟弱なやつめ
What a weakling.
Shut up, Nyanko-sensei.
うるさいぞ ニャンコ先生
お前…
You...
What is it?
どうした
Hello? Anybody home?
御免下さい 御免下さい
There's a lot of you.
やけに数が多いな
My name is Tarusaru.
垂申と申します 夏目殿ですね
I presume you're Natsume-dono?
そうだけど
That's right.
We've been asleep underwater along with the village,
我々は村と共に水底で眠っておりましたが
名を返していただきたく参上しました
so we came to have our names returned.
水底？  あのダムの村か
Underwater?
You mean that dammed-up village?
Yes. When it's filled with water, we can't go above ground as easily.
はい 水が張ると簡単には地上へ出られませぬゆえ
動ける今の間に
Now is our chance to move about, though,
押しかけさせていただきました
and so we followed you.
Takashi-kun? Have you woken up?
貴志君 目が覚めたの
Oh my, you didn't even turn on the light.
あらあら 電気もつけずに
塔子さん すいません 迷惑掛けて
Touko-san.
Sorry for causing you trouble.
Don't worry about it.
気にしないで お医者様は軽い中暑症だろうって
The doctor said it was just a slight heatstroke.
夕御飯 食べられる？
Do you think you can eat dinner?
はい すぐ行きます
Yes, I'll be down soon.
ということなんで
There you have it.
悪いけど 夜中に出直してきてくれないかな
Sorry, but could you come back later tonight?
はい
Yes.
That was the last one.
これで最後
I-I'm so tired...
疲れた
Damned fool, returning it so easily.
ばかもの 素直に返しよって
また友人帳が薄くなってしまったではないか
The Book of Friends has gotten thinner again!
Thank you very much, Natsume-dono.
夏目殿 ありがとうございました
お礼に私の魔鏡でお見せいたしましょうか
To demonstrate my thanks, I shall show you my magic mirror.
There is something possessing you.
夏目殿に何か取り付いておりますよ
やはりな どうりで匂うと思った
I knew it! I thought you smelled strange.
ひょっとしてあの時か
Could it be from that time?
私のものに手を出すとは
How dare it touch my property?
All right, I'll exorcise it.
よし 祓ってやろう
Well done.
お見事
おのれ 放さん
Damned bastard, I won't let go!
I won't let go of this child!
放さんぞ 人の子
Forgive me.
失礼いたしました
私は自力ではダムの底から離れられないので
I cannot leave the bottom of the dam by myself,
通りすがりのあなた様に取り付きまして
so I possessed you when you passed by.
どうしても会いたい人間がいるのです
There's someone I must meet!
遠くから一目だけでも
Even if it's just a glance from a distance...
A human you must meet?
会いたい人間…
So it's not about the Book of Friends?
友人帳絡みではないのか
ですので 夏目様 暫くの間ご厄介になります
So, Natsume-sama, I will be troubling you for a while.
断る
We refuse!
お前には頼んでない 古狸は黙っていろ
I'm not asking you.
Just shut up, you old fogey.
What?
In what way do I look like an old fogey?
私のどこが古狸なのだ
You're a lowly Ayakashi, and you're trying to act all strong!
低級のくせに ふてぶてしいんだ こら
And look at your belly! Don't doubt my fashion sense!
ええいこの寸胴が センスが疑うか
I don't want to hear that from someone with a weird mask on!
仮面を着けたお前に言われたくないわ
All right, I'll help you already.
分かった 分かった 手伝うよ
So, you don't have any clues?
じゃ 手係りはないのか
None, other than that he once lived in Futaba and that his name is Taniozaki.
はい かつて双葉村に住んでいたことと谷尾崎という名前以外は
双葉村 あの村か
Futaba village...
That village?
So, how many years ago was the village submerged?
で 村が沈んでいたのは何年前だ
二十年前です
Twenty years ago.
ええ？ 双葉村の谷尾崎さん？
Eh? Taniozaki from Futaba?
You know him, Sasada?
知ってるのか 笹田
No, not in the slightest.
いいえ まったく
I guess I have to prepare for a long battle.
長期戦覚悟か
俺の父ちゃん双葉村の出身だけどな
My dad was from Futaba.
汚いわね 夏目君
That was gross, Natsume-kun!
Ah, sorry.
あ 悪い
Is what you said true, Kitamoto?
北本 本当か 今の
Yeah.
あ 双葉村の者は殆どこの辺りに越してきてるぞ
Most of the residents of Futaba moved here.
父ちゃんに聞いとくよ
I'll ask my dad for you.
I don't really understand the feeling of wanting to see someone,
俺には誰かに会いたいっていう気持ちはよく分からないけど
よかったな
but you must be glad.
はい
Yes.
夏目様は兄弟いますか
Do you have any siblings, Natsume-sama?
え？ いや
No.
そうですか
I see.
お前は いるのか
What about you? Do you have any?
Yes, four of them.
はい 四人
でも皆私のせいで死にました
But everyone died because of me.
Natsume-sama, can I hold your hand?
夏目様 手を繋いでもいいですか
You're so kind, Natsume-sama.
夏目様はお優しい
That's why you got possessed.
そんなだから付け入られるんですよ
I don't want to hear you say that.
お前が言うな
You have cold hands.
冷たい手だな
Yes.
はい
No, that's not it.
いや そうじゃない
I wanted to say that they're cold, and it feels good.
冷たくて気持ちがいいって言いかったんだ
あ 夏目様 雨が来ます
Natsume-sama, it's going to rain.
I can tell.
分かるんです
雨を予言する鳥？
A bird that can predict rain?
そうか お前元は燕だったのか
I see. You used to be a swallow?
はい
Yes.
I came to pick you up, Natsume!
夏目 迎えに来てやったぞ
何やってるんだお前ら がきか
What are you two doing? Are you kids?
うるさい
Shut up.
Very long ago, I was once a young bird.
私は遠い遠い昔 鳥の雛でした
Our nest fell,
ですが巣から落ちてしまい
but then some humans found the nest and returned it to its place.
それを人間が拾って巣へと戻してくれたのです
けれど私についた人の匂いを嫌い
However, our parents came to hate us because we smelled like humans,
and so they left and abandoned us.
親鳥達は私達を棄てて去ってしまいました
兄弟たちの命が次々と消えていき 私だけが最後まで
My siblings died one by one,
and I was left alone.
I was very sad...
悲しくて悲しくて
And then...
そして私は鬼となってしまいました
I...
became a spirit.
とこらが ある日
But one day,
a human appeared and gave me food.
そんな私に餌をおいていく人間が現れました
And he would come day after day...
それは毎日毎日
彼は野良犬とでも勘違いしたのでしょう
He probably mistook me for a stray dog.
But the scent of humans he carried reminded me of the ones who had found us.
でも 私は彼が運ぶ人の匂いに
拾ってくれたものの暖かさを思い出して
村が水底に沈んだ時
When the village was being submerged,
I was able to sleep peacefully thanks to him.
私が心静かに眠れたのはあの人のおかげなのです
そうか
I see.
How silly.
くだらん
Na-tsu-me.
夏目 ほれ
Here.
It's Taniozaki's address, the one you talked about the other day.
この前言ってた谷尾崎さんの住所
ありがとう 北本
Thanks, Kitamoto!
I can smell him.
あの人の匂いがする 近い
He's close!
どうして俺にしか見えないんだ
Why?
Why can I only see them?
あんなに…あんなに…
She's so... She's so...
Why do I see them?
どうして俺は見えてしまうんだろう
Thank you, Natsume-sama.
夏目様 ありがとうございました
夢のようでございました
It was like a dream.
I have no more regrets.
もう思い残すことはありません
I will go back to Futaba.
双葉に帰ります
そんなにあの人が好きなら
If you like him so much,
帰らなくてもいいんじゃないかな
you don't have to go home.
実は取り付いてやろうかと思ったころもありました
There were actually times I thought about possessing you,
and telling him, "You damned, impertinent human!"
生意気な人間めって
But I want to sleep in the same land as my siblings.
でも私は兄弟達と同じあの地で眠りたいのです
I see.
そうか
Natsume-sama.
夏目様
Thank you very much, Natsume-sama.
夏目様 ありがとうございました
You still have time until the village submerges again, right?
でもまだ村が沈むまで時間はあるんだろう
地震とかつじ風とか火事とか飢饉とかいう
We found who she was looking for,
探し人は見付かったけど
会いたいという願いは叶えられてない気が
but I feel like her wish to meet him hasn't been granted.
Have I become attached to her?
情が移ったか
あ あの人だ
It's him!
おーい おーい おーい
Hey!
Natsume-sama,
夏目様 今日は少し疲れました
I'm a bit tired today.
Is it okay if I go rest?
先に休ませていただいてよろしいですか
Sure, good night.
ああ お休み
She's probably getting weaker.
力が弱まっているのだろう
The swallows signaled that her time to remain in that form had lessened.
燕は次第に姿を保てる時間が短くなっていった
あれ 何でまたお前が
Why are you here again?
今宵は双葉の祭りがありますので
The Futaba Festival is tonight,
so I brought some sake.
酒を持ってまいりました
The Futaba Festival?
双葉の祭り？
Yes.
はい 双葉村は闇の境界があやふやな所
Futaba Village lies on the vague boundaries of darkness,
and Ayakashi gather there once a year to hold a festival.
かつては妖ものが集まり
四年に一度祭りをしておりました
And so while the lake is dry, I thought I'd attend it, since it's been a while.
で 水が干上がっているうちに久しぶりにやっておくかということになりまして
We'd drink, dance, gamble, and race!
飲んだり 踊ったり 賭けをしたり 競走して
優勝者には一晩だけ人間の姿になれる浴衣が送られたり
[Note: A yukata is a Japanese summer garment.]
And the winner will receive a yukata that will make them appear to be human for a night.
In the literal sense, I'm in a feverish mood for the festival!
文字通りお祭り騒ぎでフィーバーフィーバーなのですよ
What did you say just now?
今何って言った
A feverish mood!
フィーバーフィーバー
いや 人間の姿になれる浴衣って
No, the yukata that makes you appear to be human!
Oh? Are you interested in it?
おや 興味がおありですか
Would you like to go, Natsume-dono?
行ってみますか 夏目殿
Where are you going?
どこへ行く 夏目
ニャンコ先生
Nyanko-sensei.
双葉祭り
To the Futaba Festival.
What'd you say?
何だと
You'll be eaten if you go to that festival!
あんな祭り行ったらお前なら食われてしまうぞ 夏目
You're Madara? Don't get in my way!
おぬしは斑か 邪魔をするな
You were going to have Natsume as a snack with your sake, weren't you?
夏目を酒の肴にする気だな
What's wrong with eating people?
人を食って何か悪い
You're a real fool to have become attached to them, Madara.
人間に情を移すとは 不抜けたか斑
夏目を食うのは私だ
I'm the one who's going to eat him!
こいつとはそういう約束だ あほ
He promised me, fool!
I didn't promise that!
そんな約束してないぞ
The story about the yukata wasn't a lie, right?
けど浴衣の話は嘘じゃないんだろう
Could you take me, sensei?
先生 連れていってくれないか
What'd you say?
何だと 夏目 お前また面倒のことを
You're going to do something troublesome again?
あんなもののために
Why would you do it for her ?
This won't benefit you at all, Natsume-dono. So, why?
夏目殿 あなたにはなんの利もないというのに 何故
何故 情が移ったからさ
Why?
Because I've become attached to her!
What's so wrong about doing something for a friend?
友人のため動いて何が悪い
馬鹿め 馬鹿ったれめ
Damned fool! Damned, stupid fool!
This is why I hate kids!
だからがきは好かんのだ
Shut up!
うるさい
There you go.
これでよし
I have mixed my blood with the ink,
墨に私の血を混ぜたので
so no one will notice that you're a human.
誰もあなたを人だと気付かない
何故ここまで
Why are you doing all this?
Because it's interesting.
面白そうだからですよ 食べてしまうより
More interesting than eating you.
The one who touches the yukata first without using their power is the winner.
妖力を使わず あの浴衣に一番早く触れた者が優勝です
It's about to begin.
始まりますよ 行ってらっしゃい
Take care.
So, you'll be staying behind in this village?
お前もやっぱりこの村に残るのか
沈んでしまうのに
Even though it's going to be submerged?
Everyone has something that's hard to leave behind.
何者にも離れがたいものがあるんです
I see.
そうか
ありがとう 垂申
Thank you, Tarusaru.
He truly is similar to Natsume Reiko.
さすがに夏目レイコに似ている
もっともレイコとはこんなに話をしたことなどないが
However, Reiko didn't talk as much.
お 始まった
It's begun.
He won't be able to win with his short arms and legs.
あんな短い手足で勝てるわけないだろう
You got it. He's so stupid, I can't handle it.
まったくだ 馬鹿でかなわん
Sensei!
先生
蹴散らすぞ 夏目
Let's go, Natsume!
Where?
どこ あの人はどこ
Where is he?
今日もあの人は来てくれるだろうか
Will he come again today?
Tsubame.
燕 燕
Wake up, Tsubame.
燕 起きろ 燕
Tsubame.
Natsume-sama?
夏目様
お早いお帰りよかったです
I'm happy you came back early.
It will rain later tonight.
今夜遅く雨が降ります
Tsubame.
燕
谷尾崎さんは今町内会の祭りに参加している
Taniozaki-san is at the neighborhood festival right now.
Wear this and go.
これを着て 行っておいて
This yukata is...
この浴衣は
燕は力が弱いから
Your powers are weak, Tsubame, so I'm not sure if you'll be able to talk to him,
話せるかどうかも分からないけど
それでもいいなら 行っておいで
but if you still want to, then go on.
Natsume-sama...
夏目様
燕
Tsubame, thank you for not hating people.
人を嫌いにならないでいてくれて
ありがとう
I love kind people!
優しいものは好きです
暖かいものも好きです
I love warm people, too!
That's why I love people!
だから人が好きです
Natsume-sama...
夏目様
Thank you, thank you!
ありがとう ありがとう
I'm going now, Natsume-sama!
行って来ます 夏目様 行ってきます
I'm going now!
And just as Tsubame said, it rained later that night.
燕の言葉通り 夜更けから雨が降り出した
I wonder if Tsubame returned to her village.
燕は村に帰れたのかな
It's easy for those who are tied to the land to return to it.
地に縛られたものが帰るのは簡単だ
She might even have gone to heaven.
案外成仏しまったかもしれんぞ
I hope so.
だったらいいな
Did you meet him?
あの人には会えたかい
お休み 燕 よい夢を
Good night, Tsubame.
Sweet dreams.
Geez! I just can't keep up with you, Natsume.
まったく 夏目 お前に振り回されるな
But you'll stay with me until the end, right?
でも先生は最後までそばにいてくれるんだろう
Does that mean I can eat you?
食っていいってことか それは
I wonder if you'll become attached to me one day.
先生も何時か俺に情が移るかな
What about you?
お前のほうはどうなんだ
さ どうかな
Who knows?
A girl wearing a flower-patterned yukata?
青い花柄の浴衣の子
はい この間の町内会の祭りで
Yes.
At the neighborhood festival the other day.
Oh, that girl.
あ あの子か
会ったよ 青い浴衣の口数の少ない女の子に
I met her, a quiet girl in a blue yukata.
そうですか よかった
I see, that's great.
I know, want to have a look?
そうだ 見てみるかい
I just got the photos from back then developed.
今上げってきたんだ その時の写真
Here.
はい
Yeah,
そうだね
I love them too.
僕も好きだよ 優しいのも暖かいのも
Kind people.
Warm people.
引かれ合う何かを求めて
I love people who pursue things they're attracted to and want to live earnestly.
懸命に生きる心が好きだよ
色づく 西空に
hi no tsukurishi zora ni
On that day where the sky was ablaze,
差し込む一筋の陽
sashikomu hitosuji no hi
and rays of light were piercing through,
yuudachi no ameagari ni
the evening rain had stopped,
夕立の雨上がりに
気付く夏の匂い
kizuku natsu no nioi
I noticed the scent of summer,
ひしめく光が照らす
hishimeku hikari ga terasu
and the crowded, shining lights.
想いに耳を澄ませば
omoi ni mimi wo sumaseba
If I turned my ear to my thoughts,
聴こえし友の面影
kikoeshi tomo no omokage
I could hear traces of my dear friends.
夏夕空 薫り立つ
natsu yuuzora kawarirazu
The summer evening sky
鮮やかな過ぎ去りし日々
azayaka na sugisarishi hibi
and the vivid passing days were just the same,
心のまま笑いあった
kokoro no mama warai atta
and so I laughed; it was just like
あの夏の思い出よ
ano natsu no omoide yo
my memory of that summer.
小狐狸的帽子
Next Time on
Natsume Yuujinchou
The little Fox's Hat
Mom, I met someone really strong and cool today!
母様 今日ね すごく強くて格好いい人に会ったんだよ
あの人も一人ぼっちなのかな
I wonder if he's alone as well?
だとしたら 森で僕と一緒に住んで欲しいな
If he is, I wish he could live in the forest with me.
よし 町へ行こう 夏目に会いに行こう
All right, let's go to the city!
Let's go see, Natsume!